Guide to the German celebratory verse (Gelegenheitsdichtung): collection, 1550-1750
Department of Special Collections
- CONZEN, Bernard. Gigantomachia, sive particularia belli Turcici.(Huldesheim], 1717., 100.; Small 4to, 17 11.
  A. history of Eugene of Savoy's victories against the Turks of 1716 and 1717 told in a series of brief events, each followed by a celebratory verse. The account begins shortly before Eugene's victory at Peterwardein and culminates in his outstanding repulsion of the Turkish forces at Belgrade. Eugene's victories are directly reflected onto Kaiser Karl VI whose troops Eugene also led. This history is dedicated to Franz Diedrich Josef von Landsberg, dean of the cathedral at Hildesheim who financed a daily Mass and bestowed many paintings and bejewelled objects, and Maximilian Heinrich Josef von Weichs, deacon to the cathedral who administered the diocese during the extended absence of Archbishop Josef Clemens.
- [TWICKEL, Ernst Friedrich von]. Die hoch-feyerlich erscheinende Neu-Stadt Hildesheim oder ausführliche Beschreibung der solennen Huldigung. Hildesheim, Wilhelm Diederich Schlegel, 1728., 101.; Folio, 10 11.
  Description of the ceremonies of the act of indulgence performed by Ernst Friedrich von Twickel, provost of the cathedral in Hildesheim and titular bishop of Botri. Von Twickel had expected to be named bishop of Hildesheini in 1724, but he was passed over and instead given the title of bishop of Botri. At the same time von Twickel took on several positions in the city government. He continuously confused his church and state roles and persecuted Protestants, so that a commission had to be appointed by the Kaiser to oversee his activities. Zedler 65, 2137. Described here are the processional, names of notables taking part, and the musical presentation prepared by Diedrich H. Montanus and Andreas H. Schultz, organist and composer at St. Lamberti (Eitner 9, 89). The text of the sonata is printed in full. Following the church celebration, houses richly decorated for the occasion and hung with symbols, pictures, mirrors, lights, etc. are described, naming the occupants. A detailed insight into ecclesiastical festivities.
- KRIEGK, Georg Nicolaus. Syncharisticum votum. Ilfeld, 1722., 102.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating Justus Christoph Bohmer becoming Prorektor at the university in Helmstedt for the fourth time, with excerpts from speeches made on his previous appointments to the position. Although not residing in Ilfeld himself, Bohmer's father, Bernhard, had been a provincial secretary there. Later in this same year Bahmer succeeded his uncle, Gerhardt Molanus, as abbot of Loccum. Roter.: Hann. 1, 211. Kriegk, schoolmaster in Ilfeld, was widely known for writing exceptional Latin. Jocher 2, 2169.
- BECKER, Samuel. Der verjilngte Phoenix, bey der neuaufgegangenen Nahmens-Sonne. Jena, J.Z. Nisius, 1692., 103.; Folio, 2 11.
  Laudatory poem for Justus Christoph Bahmer on his name-day. Bóhmer, as he later became abbot of Loccuin, apparently gave this copy to the monastery. An early 18th century hand on the title-page reads: Donum Reverendissime Abbatis Luccensis Christophori.
- OTTO, Heinrich Bartholomaeus. Strena Montosa. Jena, Paul Ehrich,1697., 104.; Folio, 2 11.
  This New-Year's wish in verse to Friedrich von Steinberg, councillor of the Duke of Braunschweig-Lüneburg, is a good example of the play on names typical of Gelegenheitsdichtung. Here references to mountains - -Steinberg - - are repeatedly employed.
- LEYSER, Polycarp and Christ. Friedrich. Bey dam erwnschten Verlauff desl729ten und vergnilggten Anbruch des 1730. Jahreswoilten dem David Rupert Erythropel ... im gleichen ... Doroth. Sophia ... unsern beyderseits liebsten Gross-eltern ... bezeugen. Jena, gedruckt mit Wertherischen Scriften, 1730., 105.; Folio, 2 11.
  A New Year's wish in verse to the authors' grandparents, David Rupert and Dorothea Sophia Erythropel.
- FELDE, Albert zum, et al. Summos in arte medica honores. Kiel, Barthold Reuter, 1710., 106.; Folio, 4 11.
  Collection of 8 poems and one prose piece in German and Latin praisingCerhard-Stoer on receiving his doctorate of medicine in Kiel, withcontributions by Albert zum Felde, professor of theology and pastor at St. Nicolai, G.C. Scheihanimer, professor of medicine and court doctor,Sebastian Kortholt, Prifekt of the library and professor of poetry, S.H.Mus~us, C.M. Burchard and A.L. Knigsmann. ADB 6, 611; ADB 30,755;Jacher/Adelung 3, 758; Jacher 3, 771; Hirsch-Hübotter 1, 769; Jocher 2,2139.
- SCHNEBERGER, Paul Lemmel. Carmen elegiacum Graeco-Latinum. Leipzig, Abraham Lamberg, 1588., 107.; Small 4to, 4 11.
  Poem in praise of Nicolaus Brombs in Latin and Greek on opposing pages. The printer Lamberg was one of the most important Leipzig printer-publishers of the 16th century. Benzing, 282.
- RASCHKE, Hans Friedrich Wilhelm. Zu der Muller - und Hartmannischen Hochzeitslustin Dresden. Leipzig, Bernhard Christoph Breitkopf, 1726., 108.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating the wedding of Muller and Hartmann.
- STECEMANN, Georg. Gamelion in honorrem ... Augustini Kockerdii Doctoris, nuptias celebrantis cum ... Anna Petersen. Lübeck, AswerKrager, 1591., 109.; Small 4to, 4 11.
  Poem celebrating the wedding of August Kockerdus and Anna Petersen. Presentation inscription from the author at foot of title-page.
- [MANUSCRIPT]. ELER, Franz. Epithalamion in honorem nuptiarum. (Lüneburg, ca. 1590., 110.; Small 4to, 4 11.
  Shaved along lower edges, effecting some text. Poem celebrating the wedding of Theodor Harstrick and Catharina Bussovius.
- [MANUSCRIPT]. RHUEDEN, Hieronymus, jun. Epithalamion in solemnitatem nuptiarum. (Lüneburg, 1595., 111.; Small 4to, 3 11.
  Poem on the marriage of Friedrich Koepken and Anna Lenten, written in German and Latin on opposing pages.
- [MANUSCRIPT]. Noedenius, Georg. Gratulatorium in solemnem nuptiarum festivitatem. (Lüneburg], 1597 May 30, 112.; Small 4to, 3 11.
  Poem celebrating the wedding of Heinrich Husanus and Elisabeth Laffert. Husanus, named after his father, one of the greatest lawyer-diplomats of Germany in the 16th century, followed in his footsteps and served as a diplomat under Johann Albrecht II von Mecklenburg-Güstrow and Adolf Friedrich I. In this role he was frequently a conciliator between the conflicting powerful factions in the Mecklenburg area. ADB 13, 447.
- [MANUSCRIPT]. SEGER, Johann. Nuptiis, Dre. Henrici Husani.Lüneburg, 113.; 1597 May 30.
  Small 4to, 2 11.
- (MANUSCRIPT]. NOEDENIUS, Ceorg. Gratulatorium in solemnem nuptiarum festivitatem. Lüneburg, [ca. 1600, 114.; Small 4to, 3 11.
  Poems on the wedding of Bertius Elver and Anna Broms. The Elvers were one of the oldest patrician families in Lüneburg. The first two poems are addressed to the fathers of the bridal pair, Nicolaus Broms and Albert Elver.
- SCHROTER, Leonhart, and WEICHLER, Paul. Epithalamia in honorem venerandi yin ... Ioannis Coqui ... et ... Elisabeth Mutes. Magdeburg, Andreas Gehne, 1593., 115.; Small 4to, 4 11.
  Two epithalamia for Johann Koch and Elisabeth Frank, widow of Johann Frank, written by an important composer of the time. Schroter, cantor in Magdeburg, wrote Christmas carols, hymns, psalms, a Te Deum and other religious pieces. AIYB 32, 572; Eitner 9, 74.
- BONUS, Joachim. Gamelion in honorem nuptiarum. Magdeburg, WilhelmRoss, 1606., 116.; Broadside.
  Poem celebrating the wedding of Joachim Bonus Sr. and Certrud Hinrich, asecond marriage for both, written by Bonus' son. The senior Bonus taught at the music school in Magdeburg. Eitner 2, 128.
- FRANK, Paul Melissus, et al. In nuptias nobilis et clarissimi vir Hardevvigi a Dassell ICti. Carmina. Prague, 1588, 117.; Small 4to, 6 11.
  Poem celebrating the marriage of Hartwig von Dassel and Anna Dusterhopf.Von Dassel, son of a mayor of Lüneburg, was a lawyer and advisor toArchduke Maximilian of Austria. The following year he was appointed advisor to Kaiser Rudloph II and joined the court at Prague. ADB 4, 761.
- MANCINUS, Georg. Honori Geberhardi, Balthasaris F. ~ Moltken carmina. Rostock, Stephan Myliander (-.Mallemann), 1594., 118.; Small 4to, 4 11.
  Poems in praise of Gebhard Balthasar F. von Moltke, including an epithalamium. The von Moltkes were a noble Mecklenburg family which rose to prominence in the regional administration under Wallenstein early in the 17th century. ADB 22, 157.
- IDEN, Jacob Friedrich. Als der hoch-wiirdige, ... Philip Ludewig Bahmer ... die obgedachte Calenbergische General-Superintendentur, mit der General-Superintendentur in dem Herzogthum Liineburg ... verwechselte.Salzwedel, Christian Schuster, 1726., 119.; Folio, 4 11.
  Poem in praise of Phillip Ludwig Bahmer on succeeding to the position of general superintendent at Celle. Woven into the long poem are allusions to Bôbmer's past accomplishments which are footnoted and explained at greater length, thus giving the reader a full account of Babmer's background. Brother of Justus Christoph, Phillip Ludwig had been professor of morals at Helmstedt, general superintendent in Gottingen and for many years a councillor at the royal court in Hannover. Jocher 1, 1177; Roter.: Hann. 1, 213.
- FICULUS, Benedictus. Chronosebeia Paschalis. [Speyer], 1603, 120.; Small 4to, 6 11.
  Poems celebrating Easter, followed by a passage from Matthew which appears in both Latin and German.
- FIGULUS, Benedictus. Benedictus Figulus Utenhovius, ... carmen hoc elegiacum. [Speyer], 1604., 121.; Broadside.
  Poem written for the New Year on Christian faith.
- [HARTARD, Heinrich]. Sacerdos magnus in episcopatu Spirensi. Speyer, Gustav Rost, 1714, 122.; Folio, 8 11.
  Description of the ceremonies honouring Heinrich Hartard, Freiherr von Rollingen, as Bishop of Speyer. Although Hartard had succeeded to the position in 1711, he first received papal confirmation in Sept. 1712, but the ceremonies in Speyer were further delayed until 1714. 'It is the belated consecration ceremony which is described here. The delays were partly a result of the remaining disarray in the city following its devastation by the French in 1688-89 and the continuing French rule.
- HOCHSTETTER, A.A., et al. Q.D.B.V. Honores in theologia suinmos Christophoro Reuchlino. Tübingen, Joh. Conrad Eitel, 1701., 124.; Folio, 2 11.
  Collection of poems in Latin and German honouring Christoph Reuchlin on receiving his doctorate. By this time Reuchlin already had developed a successful career as professor of theology and pastor in Tubingen. Among those honouring Reuchlin is A.A. Hochstetter, rector of the university and professor of poetics, eloquence and later of morals. Hochstetter also had a reputation as a philosopher and was recognized as such by Leibniz. He later preached Reuchlin's funeral oration. Others writing are Rudolph J. Camerarius, Elias Camerarius and Johann Zeller. ADB 28, 279; ADB 12, 526, ADB 3, 726; ADB 3 719; ADB 45, 26.
- ENCEL, Johann Friedrich. Glückwünschender Zuruff und wohigemeint Cedancken. Tübingen, Hiob Francke, 1717., 125.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem honouring Alexander Camerarius on receiving his doctorate in medicine. Camerarius was one in a long line of noted doctors and here was presented with his degree by his father, Rudolph Jacob Camerarius, thus continuing a family tradition. Alexander went on to become professor of medicine and botany and director of the botanical gardens in Tübingen. Jacher 1, 1590.
- HOCHSTETTER, A.A., et al. Bona verba, quibus honores doctorales in arte medica, brabeuta parento collatos, ... Alexandro Cainerario. Tübingen, Johannes Conrad Reis, 1717., 126.; Folio, 2 11.
  Collection of 27 poems in Latin and German honouring Alexander Canierarius on receiving his doctorate, written by such academic luminaries as A.A. Hochstetter, his father Johann A. Hochstetter, a friend of Spener, Joh. Zeller, a doctor reknowned as an authority, both theoretical and practical, on childbirth, and many family members. The number of Camerarius' who appear here attests to the breadth of scholarship in the family: Rudolph Jacob, his father, Elias, his uncle who was doctor to the Duke of Würtenberg, and Johann Christoph and Heinrich, both still students at the time.
- PRAETORIUS, Arnold and WOLTER, Joachim. Eychai Gamikai. Uelzen, Michael Kraner, 1581., 127.; Small 4to, 4 11.
  Poems celebrating the wedding of Euricius Dedekind and Certrud Wippermann. Dedekind, a musician and currently cantor in Luneburg, was the son of Friedrich, author of the Grobianus, which was the most celebrated popular poem in Germany in the 16th century. NDB 3, 551.From the first and, for many years, only press in Uelzen. Not in Brandes.
- BOCK, Heinrich. Epithalamion. Uelzen, [Michael Kraner], 1587., 128.; Small 4to, 4 11.
  Poem on the wedding of Elisabeth Ratken and Albert Lenicer, rector in Lüneburg. Jacher 2, 2364. Not in Brandes.
- WICKELMANN, Samuel. Epithalamion. Uelzen, [Michael Kraner], 1587., 129.; Small 4to, 8 11.
  Epithalamium for Elisabeth Ratken and Albert Lenicer. The names of the bridal pair are contained in two acrostics.Not in Brandes.
- LENICER, Heinrich. Gratulationes in honorem nuptiarum. Uelzen, Michael Kroner, 1594., 130.; Small 4to, 4 11.
  Poem celebrating the wedding of Johann Gueden and Rikia Tóbing. A short poem by Nicolaus Stoterogg follows. Not in Brandes.
- FINCKS, Peter. Nuptiis ornatissimi Friderici Koepken & lectissimae virginis Annae. Uelzen, Michael Kraner, 1595., 131.; Small 4to, 4 11. Poem celebrating the wedding of Friedrich Koepken and Anna Lenten. Not in Brandes.
- FINCKS, Peter. Nuptiis praestantis virtute et eruditione yin domini Ioannis Backmeisteri. [Uelzen, Michael Kraner], 1595., 132.; Small 4to, 4 11.
  Poem on the wedding of Johann Backnieister and the daughter of Hieronymus Muller. Not in Brandes.
- EBER.HARD, Joachim. Secundis nuptiis. Uelzen, [Michael Kroner],1598., 133.; Small 4to, 4 11.
  Poem celebrating the wedding of Joachim Wahi and Elisabeth Schomacker. Not in Brandes.
- PILICHIUS, Christoph. Epithalamion. Uelzen, [Michael Kraner],1598., 134.; Small 4to, 6 1],.
  Two poems, one in Latin and the other in German, celebrating the wedding of Statius Tobing and Elisabeth Elver, the widow of Philipp Krager. Tabing was superintendent of the saltworks as well as being mayor of Luneburg for 20 years. Not in Brandes.
- HERMANN, Daniel. Carmen nuptiale. Wittenberg, Johannes Schwertel,1572., 135.; Small 4to, 4 11.
  Poem celebrating the betrothal of Johann Elias von Lemgo and Anna Tespel, written by Hermann while he was at Wittenberg finishing his humanist studies. A noted poet, particularly in Latin, Hermann turned his talent for writing to journalism when he was sent to Poland to observe and report on the war in 1578-9. His reports constitute one of the most thorough and lucid histories, but later in life Hermann devoted himself again to poetry. His widow published his collected verses in 1614. ADB 12, 166.
- RODEWOLD, Heinrich. Epithalamium in gratium et honorem nuptiaruni.Wittenberg, Clemens Schleich and Anton Schane, 1574., 136.; Small 4to, 4 11.
  Epithalamium for Heinrich Witzendorff, later mayor of LGneburg, and Elisabeth Tabing. Rodewold prefaces the epithalamium with a dedicatory poem to the bride's father, Heinrich Tabing.
- BERGMANN, Heinrich Baithasar. Joannes in Smaragdo Muri Sionis Gosslariensis virescens in viro ... domino M. Joanne Michaele Heineccio. Wolfenbüttel, Bismarck heirs, 1699., 137.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem honouring Johann Michael Heineccius on becoming deacon at Goslar. His later scholarly pursuits resulted in a history of Goslar and research on signets and seals, in which subject he is considered the first scientific researcher. ADB 11, 363. Printed by the widow of Kaspar Johann Bismarck during her six-year operation of the press.
- RITTERSHUSEN, Conrad. Ad dn. Johannem Trudisum P.L. & I.V.L. n.p., 138.; Small 4to, 2 11.
  Poem in praise of Johann Trudisus.
- B., C. Ecloga in nuptiis. n.p., ca. 1650, 139.; Small 4to, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating the wedding of Balthasar Goedemann and Elisabeth Meinich.
- KNECHT, Henneke. Dei unvermautete doch glüklike Fisch-Fank. n.p., 1721., 140.; Folio, 2 11. (1 copy)
  Poem in Niederdeutsch celebrating the wedding of Doctor Stoer and Henriette Sophie Striepen. Linke, p. 235; Borchling-Claussen 4014.